"I'm knackered - have you got any tips for a good night's sleep?"
"我累坏了——你有什么睡个好觉的妙招吗？"
Not only is sleep a common feature of our small talk, we've also spent decades trying to understand and explain it.
睡眠不仅是我们闲聊的常见话题，几十年来我们也一直在试图理解和解释它。
After all, we spend on average 26 years of our lives asleep.
毕竟，我们一生中平均有26年的时间在睡觉。
So, what do we know?
那么，我们了解到了什么呢？
Here are the highlights of the last decade of research.
以下是过去十年研究的亮点。
One of the most intriguing developments is in the study of lucid dreaming – it seems it's possible to communicate with people while they're sleeping.
最引人入胜的进展之一是清醒梦研究——似乎可以在人们睡觉时与他们交流。
In a study called 'Real-time dialogue between experimenters and dreamers during REM sleep', researchers asked questions to participants in a lucid dream.
在一项名为"快速眼动睡眠期间实验者与做梦者之间的实时对话"的研究中，研究人员向处于清醒梦状态的参与者提问。
The dreamers signalled the answers using pre-agreed eye or facial movements.
做梦者使用预先约定的眼部或面部动作来示意答案。
They were accurate, suggesting they could access their cognitive functions such as working memory while sleeping.
他们的回答是准确的，这表明他们能够在睡眠时调用认知功能，如工作记忆。
This interaction between dreamworld and reality has brought excitement to the sleep science community.
这种梦境与现实之间的互动让睡眠科学界都很兴奋。
Sleep can also help our memory and problem-solving.
睡眠还能帮助我们记忆和解决问题。
A 2023 review of research by Denis and Cairney noted that brain regions that are used to learn new things, are reactivated during sleep.
丹尼斯和凯尔尼在2023年的一项研究综述中指出，用于学习新事物的大脑区域在睡眠期间会被重新激活。
That means while we're sleeping, our brains replay our memories of what happened during the day, which is believed to be crucial for memory retention.
这意味着当我们睡觉时，我们的大脑会回放白天发生事件的记忆，这被认为对保持记忆至关重要。
And, if you've ever felt it was best to sleep on a tricky problem and solve it in the morning, you might have scientific backing!
而且，如果你曾经觉得最好先把难题放一放，睡一觉，第二天早上再解决，你可能是有科学依据的！
A 2019 study by Sanders and colleagues found that people were more likely to solve a tricky problem the next day if the problem had been activated in their brains during sleep.
桑德斯及其同事在2019年的一项研究发现，如果一个棘手的问题在睡眠期间被激活，人们更有可能在第二天解决它。
So, if you're stuck, rest up and return to it in the morning.
所以，如果你陷入困境，休息一下，第二天早上再回来解决。
What if you're unlucky enough to suffer with sleep deprivation?
如果你不幸遭受睡眠不足呢？
Unfortunately, you may be at higher risk of negative moods and worse emotional regulation, according to a 2021 meta-analysis called 'The effect of sleep deprivation and restriction on mood, emotion, and emotion regulation'.
不幸的是，根据2021年一项名为"睡眠不足和限制对情绪、情感和情绪调节的影响"的汇总分析，你可能面临更高的负面情绪风险和更差的情绪调节能力。
The good news is there are plenty of tips to help you with your sleep hygiene.
好消息是，有很多方法可以帮助你改善睡眠卫生。
The UK's National Health Service recommends having a set time to start winding down, meditation before bed, which they call 'beditation', and avoiding caffeine before bed.
英国国家医疗服务体系建议设定一个固定的时间开始放松，睡前冥想（他们称之为"床想"），并避免睡前摄入咖啡因。